<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plea for the reall-presence Wherein the preface of Syr Humfrey Linde, concerning the booke of Bertram, is examined and censured. Written by I.O. vnto a gentleman his friend.</title>
            <author>Floyd, John, 1572-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01008</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11113</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115112</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850331</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850331</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15522</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01008)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15522)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 886:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plea for the reall-presence Wherein the preface of Syr Humfrey Linde, concerning the booke of Bertram, is examined and censured. Written by I.O. vnto a gentleman his friend.</title>
                  <author>Floyd, John, 1572-1649.</author>
                  <author>Lynde, Humphrey, Sir.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 62, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>C. Boscard],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>VVith permission. Anno 1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Floyd by STC.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ratramnus, --  monk of Corbie, d. ca. 868. --  De corpore et sanguine Domini.</term>
               <term>Transubstantiation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15522:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PLEA FOR THE REALL-PRESENCE.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN <hi>The preface of</hi> Syr Humfrey Linde, <hi>concerning the booke of</hi> Bertram, <hi>is examined and cenſured.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WRITTEN by I.O. vnto a Gentleman his friend.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVith permiſsion. Anno</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15522:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:15522:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS MVCH HONOVRED FRIEND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>YR, I haue recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Booke of <hi>Bertram,</hi> tranſlated into Engliſh, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed by <hi>Syr Humfrey Linde,</hi> with a dedicatory, and a longe Preface before it, and togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your requeſt to haue my iudgement, aſwell concerning the credit of the treatiſe, as the verity of the Preface. Your ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular affection and manifold curteſies shewed towards me,
<pb facs="tcp:15522:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:15522:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15522:4"/>
ioyned with your ſo religious loue of the Catholike truth, haue ſo obliged my ſelfe and my ſtudyes vnto you, as I may not be backeward in yeelding vnto your ſo pious and iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. For I know your require this Cenſure not for your own ſatisfaction (who are better grounded, then to be remoued, or moued with the vanity of ſuch a trifle) but for the more full information of ſome of your friends, whome <hi>Syr Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi> would engage to run the ſame vnaduiſed courſe with himſelfe, who doth<note n="(a)" place="margin">Praefa. fol. 3. b. lin 21. &amp; fol. 14. b. lin. 16.</note> 
               <hi>engage the credit of his Religion, &amp; the ſurety of his Saluation vpon the worthines of this Tracte.</hi> I haue
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15522:4"/>
heerin exceeded the breuity of a Cenſure, as being deſirous to lay open not only the inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of <hi>this Preface,</hi> to preuent the Readers danger, but alſo briefly the verity of the Reall-preſence, for the Prefacers, by me deſired, conuerſion vnto the Catholike church. The worke being wholly and total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yours by the free &amp; full gift of the Authour, you may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thereof at your pleaſure, and if you iudge the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixe, you may ſelect ſuch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles thereof, as you shall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme moſt fit to be ſent to your friends, and to accept of the whole (as I know you will)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15522:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
with the ſame affection as it is offered vnto you by him, who doth euer reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſeruant in Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>I.O.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15522:5"/>
            <head>A PLEA FOR THE REALL-PRESENCE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE are fiue points about which you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſatisfaction touched in <hi>Syr Humfreys</hi> Preface. Firſt concerning the deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Iury of the diſſenſion of Catholike Authors about <hi>Bertram.</hi> Secondly the truth concerning the Author and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the booke. Thirdly, concerning the fidelity of the tranſlation therof into Engliſh. Fourthly, concerning the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Gods word about the Reall-preſence. Fiftly, concerning the belief in this point of the Church of the nynth age wherein <hi>Bertram</hi> liued, whereof <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> doth much preſume, and ſeems to preferre the ſame before the word of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15522:6"/>
Chriſt, as shall appeare. Theſe pointes I will declare with the moſt breuity and clarity I may.</p>
            <div n="1" type="point">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE FIRST POINT.</hi> Syr Humfrey conuicted eyther of falshood or groſſe ignorance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Iury.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COncerning the Iury of Catholikes about <hi>Bertram,</hi> the Preface vttereth many vntruths, ſhewing (if this be done wittingly) the falſhood (if vnwittingly) the ignorance of the authour and that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well about the nature of thinges, as in the latin tongue.</p>
               <p>In the firſt kind, he hath ſix groſſe errours and miſtakings, vpon which are grounded the ſix pretended diſſenſions of the twelue Catholick (by him choſen) Iurors, to goe vpon <hi>Bertram</hi> his doctrine and booke.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, not to diſtinguiſh betw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ixt writing darkely of the truth, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly againſt the truth. By this miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king he impoſeth a falſhood vpon Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15522:6"/>
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> the Foreman of the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſo maketh a iarre betwixt him and<note n="(c)" place="margin">Preface fol. 7. b. lin 1. &amp; fol. 4. b. lin. 6. 8. fol. 5. lin. 5.</note> F. <hi>Perſons,</hi> the ſecond of the Iury who ſayth, that <hi>Bertram</hi> dyed Catholike and neuer taught hereticall doctrine: but this booke after his death hath been cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by heretikes. This verdict is the truth as ſhall afterward appeare. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſay to the contrary that <hi>Bertram was a ſingular No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelict, or that he was oppoſed for his hereticall doctrine.</hi> Theſe are <hi>Syr Humfreys</hi> miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, not <hi>Bellarmines</hi> aſſertions. <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> only ſayth, that <hi>Bertram</hi> (and <hi>Scotus</hi> before him) <hi>writ doubtfully of the truth, &amp; moued questions about the Reall preſence, yet</hi> (ſayth<note n="(d)" place="margin">Bellar. l. 3. de Eu. char. c. 8. §. iam ſententia.</note> he) <hi>neither they, nor any other in that age did teach openly againſt it.</hi> So that by Cardinall <hi>Bellarmines</hi> iudgment <hi>Bertra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> might be Catholicke in his opinion, as F. <hi>Perſons</hi> ſayth, though for his darke writing he were miſliked.</p>
               <p>The ſecond errour, is to thinke that if one write truely in ſenſe, he is not to be condemned for vſing darke &amp; doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſpeech againſt the ſtyle of the church. Vpon this errour is built the ſecond op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition betwixt the two next Iurors. Becauſe <hi>Langdalius</hi> ſayth: <hi>Bertram</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Preface fol. 5. a. circa fine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; b. init.</note> 
                  <hi>for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15522:7"/>
ſenſe held the Catholicke doctrine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. epiſt. 188.</note> 
                  <hi>but tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed in the forme of wordes,</hi> Syr Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey inferres, that then <hi>Garetius</hi> had no reaſon to ſay, that <hi>Bertram</hi> writ fondly or dotingly. As though to croſſe the tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church though but in forme of words were not <hi>Dotage or inſolent mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> and againſt the preſcript of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle:<note n="(g)" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Shune prophane nouelty of ſpeech: Vſe</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">2. Tim. 1.13.</note> 
                  <hi>the forme of ſound words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third errour, is to make the publiſhing of doctrine againſt the truth, and the publiſhing of a booke that writs darkly of the truth, to be the ſame. By this errour, he putteth varia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<note n="(i)" place="margin">fol. 6. lin. 4.</note> betwixt D. <hi>Sanders</hi> ſaying: <hi>The Sacramentarian do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was not published in Bertra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s age.</hi> And M. <hi>Reynoldes,</hi> who affirmes, <hi>That Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram</hi> (as Scotus had done before him) <hi>writ doubtfully of the truth of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> What oppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I pray you betwixt theſe two ſentences, that <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> ſhould ſay they hold togeather, <hi>like</hi>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">fol. 5. lin. vltim.</note> 
                  <hi>a rope of ſande?</hi> Yea, doth not the ſaying of M. <hi>Reynolds</hi> confirme the ſaying of D. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders?</hi> For if (as M. <hi>Reynoldes,</hi> ſayth) euen <hi>Bertram</hi> and <hi>Scotus</hi> that are moſt challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in this matter, taught not ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarian doctrine openly, but only writ
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15522:7"/>
doubtfully of the truth, then moſt true is the ſaying of D. <hi>Sanders,</hi> that the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarian doctrine was not published or taught publiquely in that age. Is it not great ſeelines to challenge thoſe ſpeeches as contradictious and holding togeather <hi>as a rope of ſande,</hi> which ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and are ſo knit togeather as the one includeth the other?</p>
               <p>The fourth errour, to thinke that one cannot be the diſciple or follower of one that is dead many hundred yeares: according to which errour men now li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing could not be the diſciples and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of the Apoſtles, and of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. This is the ground of the diſcord he deuiſeth betwixt the ſeauenth and eighth of the Iury. Becauſe <hi>Valentia</hi> ſayth, that <hi>Bertrams</hi> book is taynted with the leuen of <hi>Berengarius</hi> his errour; <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi>
                  <note n="(l)" place="margin">Fol. 6. a lin. 20.</note> vrgeth his ſaying as oppoſite vnto <hi>Poſſeuinus,</hi> that <hi>Oecola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>padius</hi> corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the booke, and ſet it out vnder <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trams</hi> name, for (ſayth <hi>Syr Humfrey) Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rengarius</hi> liued 600. yeares agoe, and <hi>Oecolampadius</hi> an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred. As who ſhould ſay <hi>Oecolampadius</hi> could not be a Beren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garian in opinion, &amp; infect bookes with that leuen, becauſe he liued fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15522:8"/>
yeares after <hi>Berengarius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fifth errour, is to thinke, that Catholickes, who ſay <hi>Bertram</hi> writ a booke of the body &amp; blood of our Lord, do therefore affirme, this booke ſet out by <hi>Oecolampadius,</hi> to be his booke, &amp; alſo to be pure and incorrupt without any nouell inſertion of hereticall ſtuffe. This errour is tranſcendentall in all this qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell with the Iury, but<note n="(m)" place="margin">fol. 6. b. lin. 10.</note> particulerly, it cauſeth him to conceaue a diſſention betwixt <hi>Heskins,</hi> that ſayth <hi>Bertram</hi> writ a booke ſuſpiciouſly, and <hi>Sixtus Senenſis,</hi> who ſaith, that the booke was corrupted and ſet forth by <hi>Oecolampadius</hi> in <hi>Bertrams</hi> name. A great contradiction ſure. Might not the booke that was written doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully by <hi>Bertram,</hi> be corrupted afterward by plaine hereticall aſſertions, &amp; ſet out in his name ſo corrupted by <hi>Oecolampa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſixt errour, that a pious and godly man may not write darkely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſome myſtery of fayth. Hence becauſe <hi>Eſpencaeus</hi> the 11. Iuror ſayth, <hi>Bertrams</hi> booke to be darke, obſcure, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangling his Reader, he vrgeth him to contradict <hi>Tritemius</hi>
                  <note n="(n)" place="margin">In chronico.</note> the twelfe and the laſt Iurour, ſaying: <hi>Bertram</hi> was
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15522:8"/>
a learned and Godly man, and writ a booke of the body and bloud of our Lord: yea <hi>syr Humfrey</hi>
                  <note n="(o)" place="margin">fol. 7. a lin. 18.</note> to make heere ſome ſhew of contradiction where none is, with more cunning then ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, helpeth the matter. For whereas <hi>Tritemius</hi> ſayth, <hi>Bertram</hi> writ a prayſe-worthy worke of Predeſtination, and one booke of the body and blood of our Lord, Syr <hi>Humfrey</hi> leaueth out the book of predeſtination, and turnes the title of prayſe-worthy from it, on the booke of the body and bloud of Chriſt, making <hi>Tritemius</hi> ſay: <hi>Bertram</hi> writ a prayſe-worthy worke, to wit, one booke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the body and blood of our Lord. Can this be well excuſed in <hi>syr Humfrey</hi> from witting miſrelation to deceaue?</p>
               <p>In the ſecond kind, to wit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>syr Humfreys</hi> eyther of falſhood or ignorance of latin, I ſet downe theſe ſix examples, which ioyned with the other, ſix make vp a Iury.</p>
               <p>Firſt, to winne a few yeares of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity vnto <hi>Bertram,</hi> and to make him ſeeme the great writer of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great: whereas <hi>Tritemius</hi> ſayth, that <hi>Bertram</hi> writ a prayſe-worthy worke <hi>Ad Carolii Regem fratre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lotharij Imperatoris.</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:15522:9"/>
Vnto King Charles, brother of Lotha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Emperour, he tranſlates, <hi>Vnto</hi>
                  <note n="(p)" place="margin">fol. 7. a lin. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Charles the Great the Brother of Lotharius the Emperour,</hi> which is groſſe and ridiculous abſurdity in hiſtory, euery man that hath any ſmacke of learning knowing that <hi>Lotharius</hi> was Grand-child to <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, not his brother.</p>
               <p>Secondly to the ſame purpoſe: Whereas the<note n="(q)" place="margin">Iudex expurgat Belgic. in Bertramo.</note> Doway-cenſure ſayth, that <hi>Bertram</hi> was <hi>Carus Carolo non tam ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gno quàm caluo.</hi> Deare vnto Charles not ſo great as bald, he tranſlates, <hi>Deare</hi>
                  <note n="(r)" place="margin">fol. 10. a. lin. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>vnto Charles the Great. Syr Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi> was loth that this his ſo much eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Bertram,</hi> on whoſe head he hath ſet all his credit he hath, or is like to haue, ſhould be thought to haue written to a bald Emperor, fearing ſome ſhould the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce inferre that he was a bald Authour, as they may, with as much reaſon as <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> doth conclude,<note n="(s)" place="margin">fol. 3. b lin. 5. &amp; 6.</note> that he was a <hi>Great authour, and no flye,</hi> becauſe he writ to a <hi>Great</hi> Emperour.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">De viſib. monar. l. 7 An. 816.</note>Thirdly, whereas <hi>D. Sanders</hi> ſayth: <hi>Quidam ſuſpicantur,</hi> ſome ſuſpect the booke of <hi>Bertram</hi> to be forged vnder his name, he tranſlates<note n="(u)" place="margin">fol. 5. b lin. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>ſome ſay,</hi> &amp; vpon this, and no better euidency<note n="(x)" place="margin">fol. 6. a lin. 3.</note> accuſeth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15522:9"/>
Doctour <hi>Sanders</hi> that he ſayth, <hi>The booke is not Bertrams, but ſome obſcure Authour.</hi> As though there were no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt doubting and iudging, ſuſpecting and ſaying, whereas when we haue but ſuſpition of a thing, the common phraſe is, <hi>I cannot ſay it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, whereas <hi>Valentia</hi> ſayth: <hi>Dubium</hi>
                  <note n="(y)" place="margin">Valen. de preſen. Chriſti in Euchar. l. 1. cap. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>est,</hi> it may be doubted whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Bertram</hi> be authour of this booke, &amp; <hi>fieri poteſt,</hi> it may be that <hi>Bertram</hi> writ catholikly, &amp; his booke was afterward corrupted. Notwithſtanding this ſo great cautelouſnes of <hi>Valentia,</hi> to ſhew he did but coniecture, <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> makes him peremptory abſolute, and to ſay without any doubt or feare: <hi>The</hi>
                  <note n="(z)" place="margin">fol. 6. a lin. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>worke is ſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, whereas <hi>Garetius</hi> ſayth: <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lirare coepit Bertramus:</hi> Bertram began to write dotingly. <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> tranſlates, <hi>He</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">fol. 5. a lin. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>was an old dotard:</hi> fondly and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly. For to be a dotard, and to write in one matter dotingly be differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t things ſeeing one act implyeth not the habit, yea a learned man in ſome occaſion may write abſurdly. Neyther doth <hi>Garetius</hi> miſlike <hi>Bertram</hi> in regard of his agednes or antiquity, as <hi>Syr Humfreys</hi> tranſlation
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15522:10"/>
inſinuates, by making him ſay: <hi>He was not only a Dotard, but an old Dotard,</hi> but contrarywiſe in reſpect of the nouelty of his phraſe, and for his new doting, and becauſe the former part of the booke is Catholicke and contrary to the later, which ſoundes of hereſy, a ſigne that eyther the booke is corrupted, or els the Authour when he writ, was not preſent to himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, whereas the Doway-cenſure ſayth: <hi>Non diffitear Bertranum neſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuiſſe exactè. I will confeſſe Bertram knew not exactly, how accidents ſubſiſt without a ſubstance;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">fol. 10. b. lin. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> tranſlates: <hi>I doubt not but Bertram was ignorant, how accidents exactly ſubſiſt.</hi> Had <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> beene exact and not ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in Latin he would not perchance haue ſo many wayes miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtrued a few latin wordes. Eſpecially he would neuer haue ioyned <hi>exactly</hi> with <hi>to ſubſist,</hi> which both the text and reaſon ſhew muſt ioyne with <hi>to know;</hi> for there is difference betwixt knowing and exact knowing, but no difference betwixt ſubſiſting and exact ſubſiſting. So that the Cenſure ſayth not that <hi>Bertra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> was wholly ignorant, as <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> pretendes they ſay, but only that he
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15522:10"/>
knew not ſo exactly how to declare the manner of tranſubſtantiation, as Deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in this age.</p>
               <p>I omit many other the like errours committed, as I ſuppoſe not in fraud, but through ignorance of Latine, though <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> turne, and make vſe of them to the aduantagement of his hereſy in blindenes of zeale. Theſe I haue noted, ſhew ſufficiently, that the contentions betwixt Catholikes which <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> would exhibite in his Preface, haue no other ground, but his ignorance, and miſpriſion, and therefore are like to the battailles of <hi>Lucian</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Lucian verae hiſto.</note> fought by mighty armyes vpon the Iland of Cobb-webs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="point">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE SECOND POINT.</hi> Concerning the truth of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, and authority of this Booke.</head>
               <p>THIS queſtion may eaſily be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided among them that will ſet wrangling aſide, &amp; ſeeke ſincerely after the truth, that will diſtinguiſh what is doubtfull from what is probable, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15522:11"/>
what is probable from what is certaine, euident &amp; agreed vpon, as will appeare by the proofe of theſe aſſertions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it is very probable, that this booke of <hi>Bertram</hi> was written in the Nynth Age after Chriſt, when <hi>Bertram</hi> liued. For though there be not any an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient authour that maks mention therof, none I ſay that liued and dyed before <hi>Luther</hi> (for<note n="(d)" place="margin">See Poſſem. his Apparatus</note> 
                  <hi>Tritemius</hi> the auncienteſt of <hi>Syr Humfreys</hi> Iury, and to whome he doth attribute moſt, dyed ſince <hi>Luthers</hi> reuolt from the Church) yet<note n="(e)" place="margin">See Paſchaſ. his booke de corpore &amp; ſangui. Domini. tom. 4. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliot. SS. PP.</note> 
                  <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> Abbot that liued in that age of <hi>Bertram</hi> writes in ſo direct oppoſition againſt this booke, as it is likely he writ of purpoſe againſt it, as will appeare probable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any that ſhall compare the two trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes togeather. Whence I inferre, that it is great want of iudgement in <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">fol. 4. lin. 10.</note> to contend, that <hi>Paſchaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> writ not againſt this book For heerby he ouerthrowes the very ground of all his diſcourſe; ſeeing <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> his writing againſt this booke, is the only argument that the ſame was writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> about the tyme of the nynth Age after Chriſt, &amp; affords ſome poſſibility, that it might be <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trams.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15522:11"/>Secondly it is euident, that the booke is darke, doubtfull, intricate. For this is more then apparent vnto all them that are able to iudge, and with any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency peruſe the book. And to omit diuers darke paſſages of his booke, and particulerly where he<note n="(g)" place="margin">Vide l. Bertram. in catalog. Teſt. verit. l. 10. col. 1602.</note> ſeems to teach moſt cleerely the fooliſh and impious Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxe of <hi>Beza, That</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſ-belgart &amp;c contra Heſſus. p. Corpus Chriſti no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tantum ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacia ſed etiam eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pore A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahae ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titit.</note> 
                  <hi>the body of Chriſt did truly and ſubſtantially exiſt before his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation in the wombe of the Virgin.</hi> This is a manifeſt ſigne of <hi>Bertrams</hi> obſcurity, that euen ſome Catholikes thinke the book inclineth vnto the Sacramentarian doctrine, againſt Tranſubſtantiation: &amp; on the other ſide, euen Proteſtants ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that the booke fauoureth Tranſubſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In ſo much as the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Proteſtant hiſtorians of <hi>Magdeburge</hi> write: <hi>Semina</hi>
                  <note n="(i)" place="margin">Cont. 9. c 4. §. de caena. col. 212.</note> 
                  <hi>tranſubstantiationis habet Bertramus.</hi> Bertrams little booke contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſeedes and originall ground of Tranſubſtantiation. Which is confirmed by the teſtimony of<note n="(k)" place="margin">De verbis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut.</note> 
                  <hi>Paſchaſius,</hi> who writing againſt this booke doth teſtify, that though in thoſe dayes ſome ſpake obſcurely about the Reall preſence, and out of ignorance erred, yet ſayth he, no man hitherto hath openly denyed what
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15522:12"/>
the whole world doth beleeue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, to wit, the Reall preſence, or the change of bread and wine into the body and bloud of our Lord.</p>
               <p>Thirdly it is agreed vpon, that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions haue beene made vnto this book, ſince the firſt writing therof in the nynth age. For this no Catholicke denyes, many Catholicks conſtantly affirme, the parts of the book ſo diſſona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in doctrine, the one from the other confirme: The<note n="(l)" place="margin">Index expurg. Belg. Non obſcurè infuſa &amp; inſerta.</note> Doway-cenſure vnto which <hi>Syr Humfry</hi> doth appeale, conſents and giues ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, that the booke hath beene corrupted, and that this is manifeſt. Finally<note n="(m)" place="margin">Ioſias Simler. in Biblioth. vniuer. &amp; concord. Gen.</note> Proteſtants themſelues confeſſe, that when they<note n="(n)" place="margin">cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Duace<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. in Bertra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> firſt printed the booke in this age, to wit, <hi>Coloniae anno</hi> 1532. that the ſame was printed with additions: <hi>Additis Augustini, Ambroſij, &amp; Euſebij ſuper ea re ſententijs,</hi> The ſentences of <hi>Auguſtin, Ambroſe,</hi> and <hi>Euſebe</hi> being added there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. And if the ſentences of <hi>Auguſtine, Ambroſe, Hierome,</hi> (for in lieu of <hi>Euſebe</hi> they ſhould haue ſayd <hi>Hyerome</hi> out of whome ſome ſentences are challenged in this treatiſe, but none out of <hi>Euſebe</hi>) if I ſay theſe ſentences were added vnto the booke, as Proteſtants confeſſe, then
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15522:12"/>
alſo the inferences and conſequences fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med thereupon were added, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the greateſt and moſt ill-ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding part of the booke.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, it is exceeding doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, whether <hi>Bertram</hi> were the Authour of this booke, whereof neyther <hi>Syr Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey,</hi> nor any man els hath brought ſo much, as a good coniecturall proofe. For though it be probable the booke was written in <hi>Bertrams</hi> age, yet it doth not thereupon ſtrayghte follow, it was written by <hi>Bertram,</hi> yea there be better coniectures for the contrarary. For if <hi>Bertram</hi> had beene authour of this booke written againſt the Reall Preſence, as <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> thinkes: certainly <hi>Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> would haue named <hi>Bertram</hi> for his predeceſſour, and which yet he neuer did. For why not <hi>Bertram</hi> aſwell as <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annes Scotus</hi> that was in the ſame age with <hi>Bertram,</hi> whoſe booke the ſayd <hi>Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> did magnify, becauſe written doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully of the Reall preſence, calling him his maiſter, and<note n="(o)" place="margin">Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>francus in libro cont Berenga.</note> 
                  <hi>extolling him</hi> aboue the more ancient Fathers. Agayne if that booke had beene publiſhed in that age with <hi>Bertrams</hi> name, <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> who wrote againſt that booke, would not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15522:13"/>
haue ſpared <hi>Bertrams</hi> name, but haue written againſt him by name, ſo to haue impayred his credit, that otherwiſe might giue authority to the errour. Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeeing he named ſome of that age, that ſpoke and wrote darkely of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Preſence, as <hi>Feuedardus</hi> the knight. Why, was there neuer any mention of <hi>Bertram</hi> as inclining vnto the Doctrine of <hi>Berengarius</hi> if he were authour of this booke? yea the Proteſtant Pantaleon<note n="(p)" place="margin">crono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph. p. 65.</note> making a Catalogue of the workes of <hi>Bertram,</hi> leaueth out this pretended booke.</p>
               <p>Finally it is certaine, that though <hi>Bertram</hi> were authour of this booke, and the ſame written directly againſt Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, yet this is a matter of ſmal moment for Proteſtants, and not a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient warrant that there hath beene ſo much as one Proteſtant of the now En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh religion before <hi>Luther</hi> or <hi>Caluin.</hi> For certain it is that <hi>Bertram</hi> (put caſe he erred in this point of the Reall preſence) was Catholike, and againſt Proteſtants in other, as appeares euen by this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, where he vrgeth <hi>Mingling</hi>
                  <note n="(q)" place="margin">Pag. 56. lin. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>water with wine,</hi> affirming, <hi>that it is not lawfull to offer wine not mingled with water,</hi> as a thing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15522:13"/>
ſacramentall &amp; myſterious: he<note n="(r)" place="margin">Pag. 27 lin. 14.</note> doth acknowledge the dayly ſacrificing and immolating of Chriſt on the Altar in the Sacrament of his body and bloud. He ranckes Chriſme or confirmation in the number of the Sacraments with Baptiſm and the Euchariſt, giuing it the middle place, and finally priuate Maſſes, or ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration with adminiſtration and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
               <p>Hence we may conclude two things. Firſt the great vanity of Syr <hi>Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi> his preface, who ingageth <hi>his credit,</hi> to wit,<note place="margin">Preface fol. 3. lin. 21.</note> the credit of a pure profeſſour of the Ghoſpel, that is his fayth his Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon the <hi>worthynes of this tract,</hi> who ſo earneſtly and conſtantly affirmes <hi>Bertram</hi> to haue beene the authour thereof, and ſo triumphs againſt vs for a ſuppoſed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſion among our writers about this toye. This I ſay is great vanity, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being greater in his owne Church (to omit more mayne matters) euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this book of <hi>Bertram,</hi> which though <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> vrge as written by <hi>Bertram,</hi> as neuer ſince <hi>corrupted,</hi> as <hi>confuting Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubstantiation:</hi> yet Proteſtants of greater credit, are of another mind. Some reiect the book from the number of <hi>Bertra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15522:14"/>
Pantaleon: ſome confeſſe the ſame to haue beene corrupted with new additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as <hi>Ioſias Simlerus.</hi> Some contemne it as ſauouring of Papiſtry, namely of Tranſubſtantiation, as <hi>Illyritus.</hi> And ſeeing <hi>Syr Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>frey</hi> knew this well enough as appeares by his<note n="(t)" place="margin">Praefa. fol. 5. b. lin 12. Reynold treatiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Bruſe c. 5. fol. 27.</note> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gling a ſentence of M. <hi>Reynolds,</hi> wherein this is diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; I wonder he could be ſo ſeely and blind, as not ſee that this furious blaſt of bitter inuection againſt vs coms backe by reflexion throughly v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on his owne ſelfe, againſt whome rather then vs, he thus thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders: <hi>How</hi>
                  <note n="(u)" place="margin">preface fol. 11. a. lin. 20. &amp; ſequent.</note> 
                  <hi>comes it to paſſe, there is ſo much difference of opinions concerning Bertram? How is it their kingdome is ſo deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt it ſelfe that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not by any glew of concord, nor bond of vnity be conioyned? Some hold with Paul, ſome with Apollo, ſome allow the booke, others deny the Authour, Is the workeman, and the worke deuided? Is this the wiſedome and pollicy of the Church to crye ſome one thing, ſome another?</hi> Thus <hi>Syr Humfrey,</hi> and more of the like ſtuffe vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in the ſame tune, floriſhing blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold in his ignorant zeale, with euery word wounding himſelfe, and his owne diſagreeing religion.</p>
               <p>Secondly, hence appeares <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:15522:14"/>
his extreme &amp; intollerable ignorance in matters of fact in ſaying: <hi>That</hi>
                  <note n="(x)" place="margin">Preface fol. 8. a. lin 18. &amp; b. lin. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>P. Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the eight, and the Councell of Trent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned Bertra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without a</hi>
                  <note n="(y)" place="margin">fol. 8. b. lin. 9. &amp; fol. 9. a. lin. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>legall, proceeding with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out triall of the party, without hearing him, or his aduocate to ſpeake for him, ſeauen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares after his death, a ſtrange thinge neyther allowable in Church, nor ſtate.</hi> Thus he. And it is ſtrange that a man no better learned, would vndertak to be a writer, vnto whome we may ſay what S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi>
                  <note n="(z)" place="margin">Lib. 1. cont. Creſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>con. Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat. c. 3. Si non pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructus es cur non potius ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces?</note> ſayd to the lay-Donatiſt <hi>Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conius.</hi> Though want of learning in a layman be not blame-worthy, <hi>yet being no better learned who forced thee to write?</hi> Being voyd of learning, why didſt thou vndertake the taske of writing, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereunto obliged by calling? Firſt for (to examine his ſpeech a little) is it not groſſe ignorance in ſtate, and ſtate-matters, to thinke that men may not be condemned after their death? wherein I will referre <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> vnto Lawyers more learned them himſelfe, and vnto that famous Proceſſe of their Ghoſpell,<note place="margin">Sander. de ſchiſm. Anglican.</note> whereby S. <hi>Thomas of Canterbury,</hi> foure hundred yeares after his Martyrdome was ſolemnely arraigned and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of Treaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:15522:15"/>Secondly concerning the Church and her affaires, <hi>I</hi> dare ſay there is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man of learning that knowes not this doctrine of <hi>Syr Humfrey,</hi> that bookes and their authours after death may not be challenged and cenſured of hereſy, to be Neſtorian. Which doctrine was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly condemned in the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Vide Concil. Sanctum General. collat. 3. 4. 5. 6.</note> fifth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Councel almoſt in euery action ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of called of purpoſe, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne<note n="(b)" place="margin">Collat 8. can. 12. 13. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odorus Bishop of Mopſueſtia,</hi> and his Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian workes with ſome bookes of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret,</hi> and of <hi>Ibas</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Edeſſa.</hi> In which Councell likewiſe the Fathers anathematized<note n="(c)" place="margin">Collat. 8. can. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Origenes</hi> foure hundred yeares after his death, curſing them that ſhould thinke this not to be a practiſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable in the Church. But alas, good <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> dreamed not of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, but ſpake of condemning men after their death only out of his mothers wit, according to which, that procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſeemed to him vniuſtifiable. Beſids what more falſe, then that the Councel did not heare <hi>Bertram</hi> ſpeake, ſeeing the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners read his booke, and ſo heard him ſpeake, as plainely as dead men can ſpeake, to wit, by their writings? Fourthly, who that knowes of what he ſpeakes would ſay, that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15522:15"/>
                  <hi>Bertrams</hi> pretended<note n="(d)" place="margin">Preface fol. a. can. 19.</note> Aduocats, were not admitted to ſpeake for him? For were they not cyted and ſummoned thither with licence, liberty, yea in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treatyes to ſpeake freely their mind and produce the proofes of their doctrine? And becauſe they made ſhew to feare danger, had they not<note n="(e)" place="margin">See this ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct ſeſſ. 13. 14. 15. eos omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cijs vt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitat, ita etiam co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plectetur.</note> ſecurity from the Pope, from he Emperour, from the Councell, from the Catholike Princes? The truth is, that being guilty of the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood &amp; impiety of their Religion, they durſt not appeare, though <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> telleth vs a tale of a Tubb, or, which is as good, of a Purita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pulpit: <hi>That they were not admitted to ſpeake.</hi> Finally his whole diſcourſe is framed and founded vpon this falſhood, that <hi>Bertam</hi> and his booke was in the Councell, and by the Pope condemned of hereſy, whereas the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the author was not touched with any cenſure, nor the booke condemned as hereticall, but only forbidden not by the Councell, but by a commiſſion fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Councell, as being darke, obſcure, ful of ignorant phraſes, corrupted by he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes.<note place="margin">Fol 8. a. lin. 14.</note> And this is alſo the iudgement of the Doway-cenſure, to which from the Councell, and Pope, <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> doth appeale in <hi>Bertrams</hi> name; for it ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſureth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15522:16"/>
that booke,<note place="margin">See this cenſure in Indice ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgat. ſet out by Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius ann. 1699.</note> as of no worth, as darke, as full of ignorances, as corrupted by here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, not fit to be read vulgarely by Catholikes. Then add, which the Coù<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell did neuer deny, that the booke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purged from hereticall inſertions, &amp; cleared by the ſtarres of marginall anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation ſet ouer againſt the darke paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges therof, may be read without danger. Whence appeares the ſeelines of <hi>Syr Humfreys</hi> ſayd appeale from Pope and Councell vnto theſe Doway-cenſurers, concerning whome he hath this ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wherin euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that knows any thing, wil ſee there is not one true word as may likewiſe be ſeen by the references in the margent: <hi>They heare</hi>
                  <note n="(1)" place="margin">Who was choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pope 20. years after</note> 
                  <hi>the Popes ſentence, the Councels</hi>
                  <note n="(2)" place="margin">That neuer was made.</note> 
                  <hi>decree, the</hi>
                  <note n="(3)" place="margin">Who made no iudgment, but asked counſell of Doway.</note> 
                  <hi>Inquiſitours ſeuere iudgment: they weigh ſoberly his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers reaſons: they examine diligently the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour himſelf, &amp; finding the former doome</hi>
                  <note n="(4)" place="margin">Which they confirme.</note> 
                  <hi>too heauy for ſo ſleight errours committed by him</hi>
                  <note n="(5)" place="margin">Conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning the booke, as darke, ignorant, corrupted by heretikes.</note> 
                  <hi>they repeale the ſentence, and vpon more mature deliberation had of the</hi>
                  <note n="(6)" place="margin">They hold his doctrine, not to be againſt the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
                  <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, and of the doctrine, with the conſent</hi>
                  <note n="(7)" place="margin">He forſooth, gaue his conſent, that Doway ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale the decree of pope and Councell.</note>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:15522:16"/>
                  <hi>of Philip the ſecond, and the Duke of Alba, to all</hi>
                  <note n="(8)" place="margin">The booke of Index ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgatori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitours not for all Catholiks.</note> 
                  <hi>the Romish Catholikes in his behalfe ſend greeting.</hi> And then hauing ſet down the cenſure of Doway, corruptedly, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting that part, wherein they affirme, that it is manifeſt that the booke was cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by Proteſtants in their firſt editio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thereof at <hi>Colen,</hi> he concludes: <hi>Heere then is their laſt definitiue ſentence:</hi> which ſaying of his is ſufficient to define (wher the matter is otherwiſe doubtfull) that <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> his ignorance is intollerable, &amp; euen ridiculous in one that preſumes to be a writer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="point">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE THIRD POINT.</hi> That <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> in his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hath moſt groſſely corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the booke of <hi>Bertram.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOW let vs paſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Preface to the Tranſlation which I take to be <hi>Syr Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>freys;</hi> for though he not directly ſo affirme, yet he inſinuates ſo much, and his adorning the ſame with a <hi>Dedicatory,</hi> with a long <hi>Preface,</hi> his ingaging <hi>all the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15522:17"/>
credit he hath, and is like to haue in his church, vpon the worthynes thereof,</hi> ſhewes him the Authour. And makes me feare that he would take it ill, ſhould I ſuſpect the Tranſlation to be any others then his owne. Wherefore that <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> may receaue his doome from <hi>Bertrams</hi> owne mouth, of whome he doth ſo bragge, I will in lieu of a Iury produce twelue places of <hi>Bertrams</hi> book, making ſo clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for tranſubſtantiation &amp; Catholik do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,<note place="margin">Catalog. Teſtium veritatis, l. 10. anno 1568 apud Iacobum Staer, &amp; Ia. cobum Chouet.</note> as <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> had no other way to hide the matter, but to tranſlate the places falſely, and that with exceſſiue audacity. The latin, according to which I examine <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> his tranſlation, is ſet forth by Proteſtants in their booke tearmed <hi>Catalogus Testium veritatis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt place is pag. 4. lin. 19. <hi>That bread which by the Miniſtery of the Prieſt is made the Body of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Catalogus teſtiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> col. 1058. circa finem.</note> 
                  <hi>doth shew one thing outwardly to mans ſenſes, and ſoundeth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing inwardly to the mind of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; outwardly indeed the</hi> Forme <hi>of bread, which</hi> Subſtance <hi>it was before, is ſet out, the colour thereof is shewed, the ſauour tasted, but inwardly a thing farr differing is ſet forth, yea much more pretious and excellent, becauſe diuine, becauſe heauenly, to wit, the body of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15522:17"/>
Chriſt.</hi> Fittly doth <hi>Bertram</hi> ſpeake in the behalfe of Tranſubſtantiation: and <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> aſhamed to ſee ſuch papiſtry in him, ſeekes by miſ-tranſlation to lay a couer ouer it. Firſt, whereas <hi>Bertram</hi> ſayth, <hi>efficitur,</hi> bread is made, by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Prieſt, the body of Chriſt, he tranſlates, <hi>becomes the body.</hi> Secondly whereas <hi>Bertram</hi> ſayth: <hi>Aliud longè preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſius &amp; excellentius oſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditur,</hi> another more pretious and more excellent thing is ſhewed, he tranſlates, <hi>Is more pretious and excellently shewed.</hi> Thirdly and principally, wheras <hi>Bertram</hi> ſayth: <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriùs quidem panis quod ante fuerat forma, pretenditur. The forme of bread (which thing or ſubstance before it was) is shewed,</hi> he tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſlats, <hi>Outwardly the forme of bread which it had before is shewed.</hi> Moſt falſely and groſſely. Firſt he makes the ſubſtantiall verbe <hi>fuerat,</hi> which ſignifyes ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tially to be, to ſuppoſe, for <hi>habuerat</hi> the accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall verbe, which ſignifyes the being of thinges as adiacent vnto ſubſtance, not the prime and ſubſtantiall being. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly <hi>quod,</hi> which is heere taken ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely, and ſignifyes the thing or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of bread, which quiddity, or eſſence of bread, <hi>Bertram</hi> ſayth before
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15522:18"/>
conſecration was, but after conſecration is not. <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> taks <hi>quod</hi> adiectiuely, referring the ſame vnto <hi>forma,</hi> the forme and ſhape of bread, ſo conſtruing the text, <hi>Forma quod ostenditur,</hi> which is ſuch childiſh and ſhamefull ignorance, as it is vnworthy to be noted: yet by this igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance he peruerts the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours meaning.</p>
               <p>The ſecond place is pag. 7. lin. 11. <hi>VVhat I pray you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Catal. col. 1059. circa me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium.</note> 
                  <hi>can be more abſurd then to take Bread to be flesh, and to affirme VVine to be bloud? And a myſtery it cannot be, in which there is no ſecret or hidden thing contayned. And how can it be ſayd to be Chriſts body, in which is not knowne that there is any change made.</hi> Thus <hi>Bertram. Syr Humfrey</hi> in the margent noteth, that heere <hi>Bertram</hi> proues, that no change is made in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements of the ſupper: cleare againſt the drift of <hi>Bertram,</hi> who by all meanes la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to proue, that the bread is changed not by change according to ſenſible ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents apparantly, but in the inward ſubſtance inuiſibly.</p>
               <p>This is proued more cleerly by the third place pag. 9.<note place="margin">In Catal. col. 1059. circa fine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> lin. 12. <hi>This change</hi> (to wit according to outward qualityes) <hi>is not knowne heere to be made; for nothing heer
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15522:18"/>
can be found to be changed, eyther in touching,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Catal. col. 1059. circa fine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
                  <hi>or colour, or taſt, or ſauour. Therefore if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be changed herein, it is not then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing or ſubſtance, then what it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but it is another thing, or ſubstance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe bread is</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Syr Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey heere tranſlates <hi>becomes the body not made,</hi> which word he ſtill care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. In catal. col. 1060. l. 6. &amp; ſeq.</note> 
                  <hi>Made the body of Chriſt, and wine his blood: for ſo himſelfe ſayth: Take yee and eate yee, for this is my body; and ſpeaking of the cup, he ſayth likewiſe: This is the bloud of the new testament.</hi> Thus Bertram, cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewing, that the Bread is changed ſubſtantially, but not ſo that the ſame out<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardly appeare, but is hidden and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the figure and forme of bread.</p>
               <p>This is againe made cleere by the fourth place pag. 11. lin. 4. <hi>Seeing then this cannot be denyed, let them tell vs how, &amp; in what reſpect the elements are changed, for corporally</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Syr Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially to ſignify there is no ſubſtantial change.</note> 
                  <hi>nothing is ſeene to be changed in them.</hi> Therefore they muſt of neceſſity confeſſe, eyther that they are changed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe <hi>then according to the body, and ſo not to be the thing that in verity they ſeeme, but another thing or ſubstance, which they are not</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Heer Syr Humfrey vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood nor the latin</note> 
                  <hi>ſeene to be according to their owne proper being. Or if they will not confeſſe this, they are compelled to deny, that they are the body of Christ, which is wicked not only to ſay, but alſo to thinke.</hi> This place is plaine, and <hi>Syr
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15522:19"/>
Humfrey</hi> doth many wayes by tranſlation obſcure it, as I haue noted in the marge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
               <p>The fifth place pag. 22. lin. 5. <hi>VVe are truely perſwaded that no faythfull man doubteth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In catal. col. 1062. lin. 41. &amp; ſequent.</note> 
                  <hi>but that bread was made the body of Chriſt, of which he himſelfe giuing it to his diſciples, ſayth: This is my body.</hi> Syr Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey tranſlates quite contrary. <hi>For we thinke truely that any faythfull man doubteth whether that Bread becomes Christs body,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Bertram</hi> to affirme, that euery man doubts of this cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of bread into Chriſts body.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In catal. col. 1063. lin. 6. &amp; 7.</note>The ſixth, pag. 24. lin. 1. <hi>Bertram</hi> makes Chriſt ſpeake in this ſort: <hi>Doe not thinke you shall corporally eate my flesh deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into parts or drinke my bloud.</hi> Syr Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey tranſlates: <hi>Thinke not I pray you, that you must eyther bodily eate my flesh, or bodily drinke my bloud.</hi> So that <hi>Bertram</hi> his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of carnall eating, by tearing Chriſts fleſh into peeces, <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> turnes into a deniall of ſubſtantiall eating thereof, by reall ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, wheras<note n="(a)" place="margin">Cyril. 10. in Ioa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. c. 13. cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poraliter &amp; ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> carnem. In catal. vbi ſupra lin. 12. 13. 14.</note> the Fathers in this ſenſe ſay expreſly: we take in the Sacrament the fleſh of Chriſt <hi>corporally.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſeauenth, pag. 24. lin 13. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram bringes Chriſt ſaying: Then</hi> (after my aſcenſion) <hi>the bread and wine turned into the Subſtance of my body and bloud, shall by the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15522:19"/>
mystery, or Sacrament be truely eaten of the Faythfull.</hi> A place ſo cleare, that <hi>Syr Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi> like a bat that endures not the light, would beate the ſame out by miſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation. For thus it pleaſeth him to make <hi>Bertram</hi> ſpeake, <hi>Bread and wine being turned into my body, and bloud</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">All this is added.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance thereof shall in a myſtery</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verè</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</note> 
                  <hi>be recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</hi> Firſt he addeth the word <hi>Substance,</hi> bread turned into the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſts body ſhall be eaten, ſayth <hi>Bertram,</hi> bread being turned into the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſts body, the ſubſtance of bread ſhall be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> will haue him ſay. Is this to tranſlate, &amp; not rather to peruert the meaning of Authours, and make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpeake fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly? For if bread be turned in the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſt body, how can the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof remaine &amp; be eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly he leaueth out the word <hi>truly,</hi> ſaying only it is eaten, whereas <hi>Bertram</hi> ſayth: it is <hi>truely</hi> eaten, which is a ſubſtantiall omiſſion in <hi>Bertram:</hi> becauſe <hi>Bertram</hi> in the beginning of his booke, declares that he takes <hi>truly,</hi> to ſignify the ſame, as in ſubſtance, really, &amp; not only in figure, ſo that if the body of Chriſt be <hi>truly</hi> eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <hi>Bertrams</hi> opinion, it is eaten in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance thereof really, and not only in fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:15522:20"/>The eight <hi>Bertra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> ſaith pag. 27. lin. 13. <hi>VVas not Chriſt immolated in himſelfe only once,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Catal. col. 1063. circa finem.</note> 
                  <hi>and that about Eaſter: and yet in the Sacrament not only in all the feſtiuall dayes of Eaſter, but alſo euery day he is ſacrificed, or immolated by the people.</hi> Thus Bertram, which is ranke papiſtry. Now heare <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> tranſlating <hi>Bertram</hi> not into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, but into Proteſtancy. <hi>VVas not Chriſt offered about that tyme: And yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withsta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding he is not only euery feast of Easter but euery day offered vnto the faythfull people.</hi> Thus is <hi>Bertram</hi> trimmed by <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> according to the Proteſtant cut.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In Catal. col. 1064. circa me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium.</note>The ninth, <hi>Bertram</hi> ſayth pag. 30. lin. 8. <hi>It is not ſayd, that Christ doth ſuffer in himſelf euery day which he did but once? Syr Humfrey</hi> to make this place ſound againſt the Maſſe, or dayly oblation of Chriſts body, tranſlates, <hi>It is not ſayd that Chriſt offers himſelfe euery day, becauſe he did it but once.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The tenth, <hi>Bertram</hi> ſayth pag. 41. lin. 6.<note place="margin">Catal. col. 1066. circa finem.</note> 
                  <hi>According to the ſubstance</hi> (or corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Maſſe) <hi>the creatures what they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the ſame they afterward remaine. But they were before bread and wine, according to which forme &amp; shape they are ſeene ſtill to remayne. Therefore the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15522:20"/>
thing is inwardly changed by the mighty power of the holy Ghoſt, which change fayth behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</hi> This place is too perſpicuous for Tranſubſtantiation, therefore <hi>Syr Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi> in his tranſlation makes a Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation thereof, changing the very ſubſtance of the ſenſe into his owne contrary meaning: <hi>VVhatſoeuer they were before conſecration they are euen the ſame af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, but they were bread and wine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and therefore they remayne the ſame, which is proued, becauſe we ſee that euen whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are conſecrated, they remayne in the ſame kind or forme.</hi> Surely <hi>Syr Humfrey,</hi> this is not to tranſlate Authours out of Latin into Engliſh, but to tranſlate fancyes out of your owne head into their Treatiſes. For <hi>Bertram</hi> was wiſer, then to make this fooliſh argument, which you foyſt into his booke; Bread remaynes in forme and ſhape, therefore it remaynes in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>The eleuenth, <hi>Bertram</hi> often in this Treatiſe names the dayly celebration of the myſteryes, ſignifying the cuſtome of priuate maſſes, or celebrations without communion, which <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> not e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during, ſtill aſwell in <hi>Bertram</hi> as in the ſentences of other Fathers tranſlates ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15522:21"/>
and adminiſtration, by this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to make <hi>Bertram</hi> a Proteſtant.</p>
               <p>The twelfe and laſt place pag. 42. is moſt notoriouſly corrupted,<note place="margin">Catal. col. 1067. init.</note> where for fourty lines togeather, he tranſlates not one ſentence, line, or almoſt word with correſponde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto the latin text. I will note only his corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of one line ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>Bertram</hi> hath this ſentence: <hi>Corpus eſt Chriſti quod cernitur, &amp; ſanguis qui bibitur; nec quaerendum quomodo factum ſit, ſed te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendum quod ſic factum fit. VVhat is ſeene is Chriſts body, what is dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k is his bloud, neyther ought we to ſearch the manner how it is done, but beleeue that ſo it is done. Syr Humfrey</hi> thus tranſlates: <hi>That is Chriſts body which is ſeene, that is bloud which is drunke, and we muſt not enquire how it is made, or becomes his body, but beleeue and hold, and ſo it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his body.</hi> Thus he thruſts into <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trams</hi> booke his Puritanicall fayth, <hi>Crede quod habes &amp; habes:</hi> I now appeale vnto the iudgement of any indifferent Reader to giue ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Firſt whether <hi>Syr Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>frey</hi> haue not manifeſtly corrupted the book of his <hi>Bertram?</hi> Secondly, whether the booke can be cleare againſt Tranſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, and vtterly ouerthrow the ſame, as <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> boaſtes, that in ſo many
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15522:21"/>
places makes ſo clearely for it. Thirdly, whether it be not the greateſt vanity in the world to build a Religion againſt the Roman Catholicke, and ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of their Church, vpon <hi>this tract</hi> which is ſo papiſticall, as <hi>syr Humfrey</hi> his Engliſh tranſlation is euen aſhamed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Finally, whether the Proteſtants be not in extreme miſery and beggary for want of profeſſors and recorders of their Religion before <hi>Luther,</hi> that can find no better then this Booke, and this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, wherof they bragge beyond mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="point">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE FOVRTH POINT.</hi> A grand Iury againſt <hi>Syr Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey,</hi> shewing the Reall preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, which he terames, <hi>a dead letter</hi> to be the doctrin of Gods holy word and the perpetull do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church.</head>
               <p>THE infinite wiſedom of Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit foreſeeing with what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15522:22"/>
the Reall preſence of Chriſts ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred fleſh, and pretious bloud in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament would be beleeued of carnall men, in regard of the repugnance with reaſon, the ſame ſeemes to haue in their iudgement, would haue all the holy Scriptures to ſet downe this truth, more often, and ſequently, more ſolemnely, &amp; of ſet purpoſe, more cleerely &amp; expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely, then the truth of any other chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doctrine. Out of which I gather theſe twelue expreſſe and formall ſentences in this behalfe from Chriſt Ieſus his own mouth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ioan. 6.51</note>The firſt. <hi>The bread which I will giue, is my flesh, which I will giue for the life of the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. 53.</note> The ſecond. <hi>Verily, verily, except you eate the flesh, and drinke the bloud of the ſon of Man, you shall not haue life in you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. 54.</note>The third. <hi>VVhoſoeuer eateth my flesh, and drinketh my bloud, hath eternall life, and I will rayſe him vp at the laſt day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. 55.</note>The fourth. <hi>My flesh is meate indeed, my bloud is drinke indeed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. 58.</note>The fifth. <hi>This is the bread that comes downe from heauen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. 57.</note>The ſixt. <hi>As the liuing Father hath ſent me, and I liue by the Father: ſo he that eateth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15522:22"/>
me, he shall liue by me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſeauenth.<note place="margin">Ibid. 56.</note> 
                  <hi>He that eateth my flesh, and drinketh my bloud, dwelleth in me, and I in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The eight.<note place="margin">Ibid. 59.</note> 
                  <hi>Not as your Fathers did eate the Manna in the wildernes, and are dead: He that eateth this bread, shall liue for euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The nynth.<note place="margin">Mat. 26. v. 26. 27. &amp; 28.</note> 
                  <hi>And as they were eating, Ieſus tooke bread, bleſsed, brake, gaue to his diſciples, ſaying: Take, eate, This is my Body. And he tooke the cup, and gaue thankes, and gaue to them ſaying: Drinke yee all of this; for this is my Bloud which shall be shed for many vnto the remiſsion of ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The tenth.<note place="margin">Marc. 14. v. 22. 23. &amp; 24.</note> 
                  <hi>And as they did eate, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus tooke bread, and bleſſed, and brake, and gaue to them, ſaying: This is my Body. And he tooke the cup, and when he had giuen tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, he gaue to them, and they drunke all thereof, and he ſayd to them: This is my Bloud of the new Teſtament, that is shed for many.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The eleuenth.<note place="margin">Luke 22.7 19. &amp; 20,</note> 
                  <hi>He tooke bread &amp; gaue thankes, and brake, and gaue to them, ſaying: This is my Body, which is giuen for you. Like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe alſo the cup, after ſupper, ſaying: This cup is the new Teſtament in my Bloud, the cup that is shed for you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The twelfth.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11. v. 24. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Our Lord Ieſus the ſame night in which he was betrayed, tooke bread,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15522:23"/>
and when he had giuen thankes, brake, and ſayd: This is my Body that shall be giuen for you. This doe in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of me. In like ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Cup, when he had ſupped, ſaying: This cup is the new teſtament in my Bloud.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What could be ſpoken more cleare, more expreſſe? wherein will Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts beleeue Chriſt vpon his bare word, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting thereunto their carnall fancyes, ſince they contradict the truth of this his text ſo reiterated in Scripture? Reiecting the ſame as a dead letter that killeth, as doth our <hi>Syr Humfrey?</hi> Againſt whome, to proue theſe wordes are to be taken in the litterall ſenſe, I will bring one only argument, but that vſed by all the ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Fathers, and conuincing. The word of holy Scripture is to be vnderſtood in the litterall ſenſe, when that ſenſe is ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wicked, nor abſurde. This is a rule deliuered by<note n="(a)" place="margin">Lib. 3. de doctr. chriſtian. cap. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> and recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of all handes, els if it be lawfull by metaphore to deſtroy the literall ſenſe of Scripture, when without inconuenience the ſame may be vnderſtood litterally; we ſhall neuer be certaine of any ſenſe, but men wil turne and toſſe the word of God by figuratiue conſtruction, as they pleaſe. But the litteral ſenſe of this word
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15522:23"/>
of Chriſt, <hi>This is my body,</hi> is neyther wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked nor abſurd, as I thus demonſtrate. The ſenſe of Scripture, that is poſſible vnto God, is neyther wicked nor abſurd; for God can neyther be authour of a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thing, becauſe he is infinitly good, nor of an abſurd thing, becauſe he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitly wiſe: but the litteral ſenſe of this place, to wit, that bread is become really and ſubſtantially the body of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing changed into the ſubſtance therof, is poſſible vnto God. Who dares deny this? Proteſtants though ſome<note n="(b)" place="margin">Calu. lib. 4. inſt. c. 17. §. 24.</note> of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter between the teeth againſt the omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency of God, yet I haue not read any that doth in plaine terrmes affirme, that God cannot turne the ſubſtance of bread into the ſubſtance of his body. Yea<note n="(c)" place="margin">Conf. Wittemb. cap. 144.</note> ſome profeſſe they beleeue this to be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and that they would<note n="(d)" place="margin">Melan. epiſt. ad Carolum Geralit.</note> rather burne then ſay that God cannot put the ſame body in many places at once. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Catholicke, that is the litterall ſenſe of Chriſt his word, <hi>This is my body,</hi> is poſſible vnto God. And this is the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument (as I ſayd) vſed by the Fathers<note n="(e)" place="margin">Cyril. Ambroſ. Gaudent. Euſeb. &amp; alij apud Claud. Zants re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petit. 3. c. 4</note> who proue the Reall Preſence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt being God can do it, to wit, can conuert the ſubſtance of bread and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15522:24"/>
wine into the ſubſtance of his body and bloud. For if this literall ſenſe be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible vnto God, then it is neyther wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked nor abſurd; if neyther wicked nor abſurd, then to be receaued as the true ſenſe: if to be receaued as the true ſenſe, then alſo to be receaued as an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of fayth, being the true litterall ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of Gods word, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of a moſt mayne myſtery of Religion; &amp; conſequently the Proteſtant Metaphore that deſtroyes this litterall ſenſe, is an accurſed Hereſy.</p>
               <p>But the fault of our Aduerſaryes in this affaire, is not to beleeue <hi>more then they can vnderstand:</hi> and to colour with fine words foule infidelity of hart. Thus then yeelding vnto carnall imagination againſt the litterall ſenſe of Gods holy word, they chriſten, and cal by the ſtyle of <hi>following the quickning ſpirit.</hi> They are ſo blinded, as they cannot diſcerne the ſuggeſtions of the fleſh, from the motions of the ſpirit. For wherein they differ from vs about this Sacrament, doe they not therein agree with all Infidels that are in the world? Do not heretiks, Iews, Turkes, Pagans, beleeue as Proteſtants do againſt vs, that the Chriſtian Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15522:24"/>
is really and ſubſtantially bread, &amp; that the body of Chriſt is not really and ſubſtantially preſent therein? Yea their doggs that ſometymes lick vp the crums and bits that fall from their communion table, could they ſpeake, would they not profeſſe with their Maiſters ſo far as their ſayd maſters differ from vs; to wit, that it is bread, and not changed really into Chriſts body? And yet this carnall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant-fancy, wherein Infidels, yea brut beaſts conſpire with them, is forſooth the <hi>quicenkning ſpirit,</hi> a doctrine which only the holy Ghoſt teacheth, &amp; we wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fayth, &amp; the ſpirit of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly life, becauſe we do not beleeue that to be bread that ſo ſeemeth to fleſh and bloud, following the letter of Gods word, rather then the ſeeming of ſenſe. What can be more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd? or what alſo more wicked, then to ſay, as <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> doth, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Preſence, that is the body of the ſon of God, taken by fayth and really is, <hi>a dead letter,</hi> and a thing that killeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="point">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:15522:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE FIFTH POINT.</hi> Concerning the iudgment of the Nynth Age, about the litterall ſenſe of Chriſt his word, <hi>This is my Body.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FROM this litterall and expreſſe word of Chriſt, <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> dares appeale vnto the iudgment of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Catholicke Roman Church of the nynth age wherein <hi>Bertram</hi> liued, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therefore he tearmes his Mother; her worde he preferres before the word of Chriſt, and commends her, refuſing the word of Chriſt, as being but <hi>a dead letter,</hi> euen<note n="(f)" place="margin">3. Reg. 3.</note> as one of the two ſtrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets that ſtroue before <hi>Salomon,</hi> being the true mother of the liuing child, did wel not to allow of the word of her fellow-ſtrumpet offering her a dead body. Theſe are his wordes: <hi>The</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">Preface fol. 6. lin. 19. &amp; ſeq.</note> 
                  <hi>mother of the child, although she were a strumpet, yet would she by no meanes ſuffer her ſon to be deuided, nor accept of a dead child, though it was preſented to her, as her owne. Bertrams mother</hi> (the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15522:25"/>
Catholicke church of this age) <hi>although at the tyme of his byrth, she had lost much of her wonted modeſty, yet would she not agree to haue her bleſſed Body of the Sacrament, to be deuided, or giuen by the halfes, yea although what was offered her, Chriſt told her it was her Body, yet by no meanes would she allow of the dead letter which killeth, but of the quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſpirit, that giueth life.</hi> Thus <hi>Syr Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi> applyeth the Metaphore, &amp; (though he ſpeake of the credit he hath, or is like to haue in his Church) yet I feare, if he come to be tryed by ſome <hi>Puritan Claſsis,</hi> he may receaue the like doome and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, as one M. <hi>Hockenell,</hi> whome, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing preached before them, for his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, they reiected, <hi>Vntill</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">B. Ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. poſit. l. 3. cap. 14</note> 
                  <hi>he had taken more paynes at his booke, becauſe he iumped not meete in deliuering the Metaphore of his text.</hi> For I dare ſay, that neuer foule Metaphore was more vnha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſomly trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the purpoſe, then this is by <hi>syr Humfrey.</hi> His comparing the Church vnto a ſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet, &amp; ſaying, that with time <hi>she loſt much of her wonted and former mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty,</hi> that is, the pure profeſſion of ſauing truth, is not this againſt chriſts expreſſe promiſe: <hi>That</hi>
                  <note n="(i)" place="margin">Ioa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 14.17. and Matt. 28.20. Cypr. de vnit. Eccl. Adulterari non poteſt ſponſa Chriſti.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſpirit of truth should remayne with his Church for euer?</hi> His re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15522:26"/>
the deuiding of the bleſſed Body of the Sacrament, is it not moſt groſſe, vttered in direct tearmes againſt Chriſt his command: <hi>Take,</hi>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">Luc. 22.17.</note> 
                  <hi>deuide this among you? This</hi>
                  <note n="(l)" place="margin">1. Cor. 41.24.</note> 
                  <hi>is my body that is broken for you?</hi> Againſt the practiſe of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church: <hi>The</hi>
                  <note n="(m)" place="margin">1. Cor 10.16. &amp; Act. 5.28.</note> 
                  <hi>bread which we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide, is it not the communion or the body of our Lord?</hi> yea againſt the Proteſtant En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Church, which deuides <hi>her bleſſed body of the ſacrament, her Euchariſticall loafe into halfes quartars, yea ſometymes into twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty or forty peeces?</hi> His ſaying that Chriſt told the Church the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was her body, is it not incredible boldnes, rather then not apply a foule Metaphore, thus to cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and effeminate Gods moſt holyword, by changing his Body into her body? But that which ſurpaſſeth in blaſphemy all that can be ſpoken, is to compare the word of Chriſt, telling the Church, <hi>This is my body,</hi> with their words that preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a dead child to the mother of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing child, which was the word only of her fellow-ſtrumpet, conteſting with her and ſpeaking falſly againſt her conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Thus openly doth <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> profeſſe that it is not the Church of Rome, but Chriſt Ieſus and his word, with whom
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15522:26"/>
he and his Ptoteſtant Church ſtandes at defiance about the Reall preſence. For although Chriſt himſelfe telles the Church, what is offered her in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, is his Body, yet ſayth he: <hi>VVe Proteſtants will by no meanes beleeue, nor need we beleeue him more then that mother be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued her lying Stratagoniſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Verily, rather then to oppoſe ſo openly, and with ſo foule, and irreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent compariſon diſgrace our Sauiours word, and this word the moſt ſacred &amp; venebrable of all other, <hi>This is my body,</hi> they might with leſſe ſhame and ſhew of blaſphemy follow the councel that their Father M. <hi>Luther</hi> gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>VVhat</hi>
                  <note n="(n)" place="margin">Luth. defenſ. verb. coen. tom. 7. Wittemb. fol. 411.</note> 
                  <hi>haue you no wit? You muſt venture. Say then that the wordes,</hi> This is my body, <hi>were firſt wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the margent, and thence by ſome Papiſt thrust into the text. For you haue a good rule to proue this, and your rule is, that that is not written which ſeemeth ſuperflous vnto you.</hi> Now without theſe wordes your ſupper is full and completly ſet downe in the Ghoſpell: <hi>Christ tooke breade, gaue thanks, brake it, and gaue it to his Diſciples,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Doe this in remembrance of me.</hi> Theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des alon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine as much as you beleeue, to wit, that bread is to be eaten by fayth
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15522:27"/>
and remembrance of Chriſt his body, paſſion and death. Why then do you not raze theſe wordes, <hi>This is my body,</hi> out of your Bibles, &amp; Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion-books, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you haue not any need, or vſe, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the fayth, and the celebration of your ſupper?</p>
               <p>But becauſe the high conceit of the Church <hi>Bertrams</hi> mother, and his perſuaſion that ſhe by no meanes would allow of the Reall preſence, or the litte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſenſe of Chriſts word, <hi>This is my body,</hi> is ſo great a ſcandall vnto <hi>Syr Humfrey,</hi> I wil ſhew how much he is heerin decea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued, and how earneſt the Church of that age was for Tranſubſtantiation, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Proteſtant metaphoricall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; by producing the verdicts of twelue principall Authours that then wrote.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Paſchaſius Corbeyenſis, Anno</hi> 880.</head>
                  <p>In this Inqueſt, <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> may iuſtly challenge the firſt place, ſeeing he hath written a whole Treatiſe of this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Paſcha. de corpor. &amp; ſang. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini. c. 1.</note> wherein he may ſeeme to confute the phraſe of <hi>Bertram,</hi> that in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there is not the ſame fleſh that was
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15522:27"/>
borne of the Virgin. In this treatiſe there are as many verdicts for Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, as there are chapters, or ſentences; but this one, the firſt in his booke, may ſuffice. <q>Although in the sacrament there is the figure of bread and wine, yet after conſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is to be beleeued, that they are no other thinge or Subſtance, but the Body and bloud of Chriſt. Hence veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it ſelfe vnto his diſciples ſayth: <hi>This is my flesh for the life of the world:</hi> and that I may ſpeake a thing yet more wonderful, not any other fleſh, but that which was borne of the B. Virgin, that ſuffered on the Croſſe, that roſe vp from the graue: This is the ſelfe ſame fleſh, and therefore the very fleſh of Chriſt it is, which euen to this day is offered for the life of the world.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>2. <hi>Strabus</hi> 840.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>Laying aſide thinges doubtfull,<note place="margin">In cap. 11. prioris ad Cor.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſured by moſt certaine authority, we profeſſe, that the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of bread and wine is conuerted into the <hi>Substance</hi> of the body and bloud of our Lord: though we do not bluſh to confeſſe that we are ignorant of the manner of this
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15522:28"/>
conuerſion. The <hi>Accidents</hi> that remayne of the former ſubſtance, to wit, the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, the ſauour, the figure, the weight neyther qualify the body of Chriſt, nor inhere in it.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>3. <hi>Amalarius Treuirenſis</hi> 830.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">De officijs Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticis. l. 3. cap. 24.</note>
                     <q>We beleeue the ſingle <hi>Nature</hi> of bread, and the <hi>Nature</hi> of wine mingled (with water) to be turned into a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable or intellectuall <hi>Nature,</hi> to wit, into the nature of the body, and bloud of Chriſt.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>4. <hi>Remigius Antiſiodorenſis</hi> 870.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>They are tearmed bread and wine by Chriſtian truth,<note place="margin">In pſal. 22.</note> not that they retayne the nature of bread and wine, but only according to figure and ſhape, taſt, and odour. For he that could perſonally &amp; ineffably conioyne by his word fleſh aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed in the wombe of the Virgin; he alſo was able to turne the <hi>nature</hi> of bread and wine, into the <hi>Nature</hi> of his body &amp; bloud.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <head>5. <hi>Hinckmarus Rhemenſis</hi> 850.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>It is true fleſh, and true bloud of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15522:28"/>
Chriſt,<note place="margin">In enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mio <hi>S.</hi> Remigij.</note> which by eating &amp; drinking we take in the Sacrament, as himſelfe doth teſtify. And we that vnder the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment do verily take his body and bloud, are made by them the ſame, euen in <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> with him. In which after co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the likenes or ſhape of bread doth remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, that we may not haue horrour of bloud, but the grace of Redemption a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth in them.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="part">
                  <head>6. <hi>Alcuinus</hi> 800.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>The bread of it ſelfe is an irreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Suſtance,</hi> as alſo the wine,<note place="margin">Lib. de di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin. offic. c. 29. de celebrat. Miſſae.</note> but the Prieſt prayeth, that the ſame conſecrated by the omnipotency of God, be made a reaſonable <hi>Subſtance,</hi> by paſſing into the body of his ſonne. For as the diuinity of the word of God is one and the ſame that filleth the whole world; ſo this body, though it be conſecrated in many places and at innumerable tymes, yet are there not many bodyes, nor many cups, but one and the ſame body, one and the ſame bloud, the very ſame that he tooke of the Bleſſed Virgin.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="part">
                  <head>7. <hi>Haymo.</hi> 820.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>Becauſe bread ſtrengthneth the hart
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15522:29"/>
of man,<note place="margin">In paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Marcum.</note> and wine breedeth bloud in the body of man, therfore the bread is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily changed into the fleſh of our Lord and wine is turned into his bloud, not by a figure, not by a ſhadow, but in verity &amp; indeed. For we beleeue, that in verity it is the body and bloud of Chriſt.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="part">
                  <head>8. <hi>Elias Cretenſis.</hi> 804.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">In orat. 1. Nazian.</note>
                     <q>Nazianzen by the externall ſacrifice vnderſtands that which is performed by bread and wine, which being vpon the ſacred Table, are by the ineffable power &amp; ſtrength of the Almighty, truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted into the body &amp; bloud of Chriſt.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="part">
                  <head>9. <hi>Florus Magister.</hi> 860.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>Chriſt is eaten, when the <hi>Nature</hi> of bread &amp; wine,<note place="margin">Ad Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Miſſae</note> by the ineffable operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Holy Ghoſt, is changed into the Sacrament of the body and bloud of Chriſt.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="part">
                  <head>10. <hi>Theophilactus.</hi> 899.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>Our Lord by ſaying, <hi>This is my body,</hi> ſhews, that bread ſanctified on the Altar is his very body,<note place="margin">In cap. 24. Matth.</note> and not a figure and reſemblance therof; for he ſayd not, This
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15522:29"/>
is the figure, but <hi>This is my body;</hi> for how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it ſeeme bread vnto vs, yet by an ineffable operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is <hi>transformed.</hi> Again:<note place="margin">In cap. 14. Marc.</note> 
                        <hi>This is my body, this I ſay, which you eate,</hi> for bread is not the figure, nor the image of the body of our Lord, but is conuerted into his body. Our Lord ſayth: The bread I will giue is my fleſh, he ſayd not the figure of my fleſh, but my fleſh. But thou mayſt ſay, How is it, that I ſee not fleſh? O man, this is by reaſon of thyne infirmity, vnto which God mercifully condeſcending, retaynes the forme of bread and wine, which thou doſt vſe to feed on, but it is tranſelementated, that is changed euen according to the primor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall ſubſtance thereof, <hi>into the vertue of flesh and bloud.</hi> And againe:<note place="margin">In cap: 6. Ioan,</note> 
                        <hi>The bread that is eaten of vs in the Sacrament, is not only a certaine figure of the flesh, but alſo the very flesh of our Lord.</hi> For he ſayd not, the bread I will giue, is the figure of fleſh, but my very fleſh; for bread by the ſacred wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, by the myſticall bleſſing, by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the holy Ghoſt, is transformed into the fleſh of our Lord. And be not troubled to thinke that bread becomes fleſh: For when our Lord did liue on earth &amp; was nourished by the ſubſtance
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15522:30"/>
of bread, the bread that was eaten, was changed into his body, and became of the ſame ſubſtance with his holy fleſh: therefore now alſo bread is changed into the fleſh of our Lord.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="part">
                  <head>11. <hi>Valafridus Strabo.</hi> 830.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">De rebus Eccleſ. c. 17.</note>
                     <q>When the ſonne of God ſayth: <hi>My flesh is meate indeed, and my bloud is drinke indeed,</hi> it is ſo to be vnderſtood, that we ought to beleeue the myſteryes to be the very body and bloud of our Lord, and gages of that perfect vnity, with our head, whereof now we haue the hope, and ſhall afterward enioy the thing.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="part">
                  <head>12. <hi>Altercatio Synagogae &amp; Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſie.</hi> 890.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Cap 8.</note>
                     <q>We beleeue that before conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it is bread and wine, after conſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is the true body, and the true bloud of Chriſt, not only ſacramentally, but alſo eſſentially. And when we ſay the body of Chriſt, we do not vnderſtand the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy without the bloud, nor do ſeparate the bloud from the body, as it was ſhed, and flowed out at his woundes; but we
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15522:30"/>
beleeue the ſame body to be whole, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuided, vnder ech forme, the ſame whol in heauen, and togeather in all places where it is conſecrated, or receaued by Chriſtian men. And although we can not comprehend by reaſon, how the <hi>ſubstance</hi> of bread doth paſſe into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of our Lord, yet we are bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Councel of Nice.</hi> 796.</head>
                  <p>Vnto this Iury of Fathers we add a Iudge to giue ſentence, to wit, the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth Generall Councell, celebrated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Bertrams</hi> age, in the dayes of <hi>Charles the Great,</hi> thus defining and ſaying:<note place="margin">Act. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Read as long as thou wilt, thou shalt not find, that eyther our Lord, or the Apostles, or the Fathers did call that vnbloudy ſacrifice offered by the Prieſt, an Image, but the very Body, and the very Bloud of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>CONCLVSION.</head>
               <p>YOv haue in this ſhort cenſure, Syr <hi>Humfrey,</hi> and his religion araigned, &amp; condemned by fiue Iuryes &amp; Iudges.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15522:31"/>
Firſt by the Iury of Catholicke Authors, with one conſent auerring, and the Councell of Trent as Iudge, giuing ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence accordingly, that this Tract on which <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> doth engage the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of his Religion, is darke, obſcure, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate, corrupted ſince the firſt writing therof, by heretikes, not fit to be vulgar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly read.</p>
               <p n="2">Secondly, by the Iury of his owne falſhoodes and errours, and the Round Councell-table of the Proteſtant hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians of <hi>Magdeburge,</hi> as Iudge pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing ſentence, and cenſuring this booke of <hi>Bertram</hi> to be papiſtical, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the point of Tranſubſtantiation; ſo condemning <hi>syr Humfrey</hi> of want of iudgement, that builds his Religion againſt this point of Papiſtry vpon it.</p>
               <p n="3">Thirdly, by the Iury, or rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury of miſtranſlations offered vnto the booke, particulerly in twelue (beſides many other) paſſages thereof, <hi>Syr Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freys</hi> owne conſcience being Iudge, and condemning both this booke as being ſo papiſtical, as not fit to be truely ſet forth in Engliſh; and himſelfe of vnſincerity, in thus corrupting the works of ancient Authours.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:15522:31"/>Fourthly, by the Iury of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in <hi>Bertrams</hi> age, profeſſing <hi>the ſubsta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of bread and wine to be turned into the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the body and bloud of Chriſt, not metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically, but litterally; not by figure, but by truth; not by shaddow, but in verity; not only ſacramentally, but eſſentially;</hi> The generall Councell of <hi>Nice</hi> about the ſame tyme as Iudge, pronouncing the ſentence accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, that bread and wine to be made the body and bloud of Chriſt, not by fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, not by metaphore, but in verity &amp; really. Whereby <hi>Syr Humfrey,</hi> that dares write, that the Church would by no meanes take the word of Chriſt, <hi>This is my body,</hi> in the litterall ſenſe, and for the reall and ſubſtantial preſence of his body in the Sacrament, is condemned of being eyther deſirous to deceaue ſoules in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of their ſaluation (a thing vnworthy of a Chriſtian, much more of a Chriſtian Knight) or els as exceedingly to blame, to write and ſpeake ſo confidently of thinges he doth not know, nor vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</p>
               <p>Finally, by the Iury of Chriſts his owne expreſſe depoſition and ſentence, ſo many tymes reiterated in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and his Omnipotency is the Iudge
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15522:32"/>
that defines and declares, that heere he meant according to the Letter, or els is vnworthy of the title of Verity it ſelfe. For is it the part of exact and infinite Truth to promiſe a thing often, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly in plaine and expreſſe wordes, &amp; not to performe the ſame according to the letter, if the performance thereof ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Letter lye in his power? Chriſt Ieſus doth often and earneſtly promiſe, that bread and wine in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament ſhould be, and is, in all ages to the worlds end, his Body and Bloud, &amp; it lyes in his power to performe this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe according to the letter, by turning the ſubſtance of bread and wine into the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his body &amp; bloud, ſo making bread &amp; wine to become really and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tially, &amp; according to the letter his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; bloud in the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, vntil the worlds end. And can they think him to be Verity it ſelfe, who thinke that notwithſtanding ſo many his expreſſe promiſes, he doth not performe his word according to the Letter, though it be in his power ſo to performe it? Verily, howſoeuer they may gloze the matter in wordes, they doe not eſteeme of his word, as of the word of Verity in their
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15522:32"/>
hart; which <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> as being not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dexterous in applying Metaphores, nor wiſe inough to ponder his words as is required in a writer, doth openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe euen alſo in wordes by comparing the word of Chriſt in this point, vnto that notorious lye of the ſtrumpet, ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly recorded in Scripture, as hath beene ſayd.</p>
               <p>I will end: for what can I ſay? What can I do more? Verily if I might thereby reclayme <hi>Syr Humfrey</hi> from his oppoſing Chriſt Ieſus, and his Church, I would be glad to looſe as many drops of my bloud, as I haue heere ſpent inke to ſhew his errour. But if I cannot ſo preuaile with him, I muſt leaue him to Gods iuſtice, in the number of them deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed by the Apoſtle:<note place="margin">Tit. 3.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Qui delinqunt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prio iudicio condemnati;</hi> aſſuring him, that theſe wordes of Chriſt, <hi>This is my body,</hi> howſoeuer he now would eneruate,<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Freder. Miconium cap. 4.</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſculate, and diſgrace them by foule compariſon, will proue (as <hi>Melansthon</hi> ſayth) in the day of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolts againſt the denyers of the Reall preſence, who flye vnto Metaphores, rather then ſubmit their vnderſtandings
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15522:33"/>
vnto the irrefragable euidency of the ſacred Text, becauſe it is aboue the capacity of their carnal Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped in the Printing.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Pag.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Lin.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Fault</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Correction.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                     <cell>your</cell>
                     <cell>you</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>in m.</cell>
                     <cell>fol. 3. b. lin. 21.</cell>
                     <cell>fol. 3. a. lin. 21.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>in m.</cell>
                     <cell>fol. 14. b. lin. 16.</cell>
                     <cell>fol. 14. a. lin. 16.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>in m.</cell>
                     <cell>Preface fol. 7. b. lin. 1. fol. 4. b. lin. 6. 8. fol. 5. lin. 5.</cell>
                     <cell>Preface fol. 4. b. &amp; fol. 5.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>ouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt lin. 10</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>fol. 7. b. lin. 1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                     <cell>in m.</cell>
                     <cell>fol. 6. lin. 4.</cell>
                     <cell>fol. 5. b. lin. 5.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>ſhune</cell>
                     <cell>ſhunne</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>errour to</cell>
                     <cell>errour is, to</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>in m.</cell>
                     <cell>lin. 20.</cell>
                     <cell>lin. 10.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>this</cell>
                     <cell>his</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>22.</cell>
                     <cell>errour that</cell>
                     <cell>error Is, that</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>in m.</cell>
                     <cell>lin. 18.</cell>
                     <cell>lin. 16.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                     <cell>eyther of falſhood</cell>
                     <cell>eyther falſhood</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                     <cell>in m.</cell>
                     <cell>Concord Gen.</cell>
                     <cell>Conrad Geſ.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>26.</cell>
                     <cell>challenged</cell>
                     <cell>alleadged</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>21.</cell>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                     <cell>predeceſſor &amp; which</cell>
                     <cell>predeceſſor which</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>23.</cell>
                     <cell>in m.</cell>
                     <cell>lin. 14.</cell>
                     <cell>lin. 16.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>in m.</cell>
                     <cell>lin. 21.</cell>
                     <cell>lin. vltim.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15522:33"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>with adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</cell>
                     <cell>without admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>24.</cell>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>this</cell>
                     <cell>his</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibib.</cell>
                     <cell>in m.</cell>
                     <cell>lin. 12.</cell>
                     <cell>lin. 13.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibib.</cell>
                     <cell>in m.</cell>
                     <cell>fol. 11. a.</cell>
                     <cell>fol. 21. a</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>25.</cell>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                     <cell>Firſt for (to exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</cell>
                     <cell>Firſt (to exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>in m.</cell>
                     <cell>fol. a. can. 19.</cell>
                     <cell>fol. 9. lin. 19.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>in m.</cell>
                     <cell>fol. 8. a.</cell>
                     <cell>fol. 9. a</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>29.</cell>
                     <cell>21.</cell>
                     <cell>he not</cell>
                     <cell>he doth.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>31.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>Fittly doth</cell>
                     <cell>Thus fittly doth</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32.</cell>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>made.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>made?</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>33.</cell>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>appeare</cell>
                     <cell>appeares</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>35.</cell>
                     <cell>7. 8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>the ſubſtance thereof</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>(the ſubſtance therof)</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibib.</cell>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                     <cell>in</cell>
                     <cell>into</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>18.</cell>
                     <cell>Chriſt</cell>
                     <cell>Chriſts</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>39.</cell>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>recorders</cell>
                     <cell>recordes</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>40.</cell>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>ſequently</cell>
                     <cell>frequently</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>42.</cell>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>text</cell>
                     <cell>truth</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>44.</cell>
                     <cell>18.</cell>
                     <cell>then</cell>
                     <cell>their</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>46.</cell>
                     <cell>in m.</cell>
                     <cell>fol. 6. lin. 19.</cell>
                     <cell>fol. 1. lin. 19.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>49.</cell>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Stratagonist</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Antagoniſt</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>53.</cell>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ſustance.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ſubstance.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
